Thomas Gray Manuscripts:
Thomas Gray Archive
- Poems, [ca. 1725]-1771; mss.poems
  - The Progress of Poesy. A Pindaric Ode, Awake, Aeolian lyre, awake; 1757; poems.pppo
    - Ode, in the Greek Manner, 26 December 1754; mss.0139; poems.pppo; 4 autograph fair copy 240 mm x 191 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 194, vol. i, 412-418 (subscription required)
      Starr, Gray's Craftsmanship (1946), particularly pp. 422-424
      Autograph fair copy, here entitled Ode, in the Greek Manner and including the headings "Strophe", "Antistrophe", and "Epode", sent in and preceding a letter to Thomas Wharton, 26 December 1754.
    - [untitled], [29 December 1756]; mss.0140; poems.pppo; 1 autograph, partial [ll. 1-24]; HULI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 116, 90
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 231, vol. ii, 490-492 (subscription required)
      Autograph, here untitled, of ll. 1-24, in a letter to Edward Bedingfield, [29 December 1756].
    - [untitled], [before 1768]; mss.0141; poems.pppo; [?] autograph, partial [notes only]; MOLI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 117, 90
      Jones, Thomas Gray, Scholar (1937), "Register of Gray Autograph Manuscripts", VI. 20(b) Ode to Poesy, 181
      Autograph, revised, notes to the poem, in Gray's copy of Odes by Mr. Gray ( 1757 ). The notes were first published in the poem's version in Poems ( 1768 ).
    - [untitled], [1?] February 1768; mss.0142; poems.pppo; 3 autograph, partial [motto, advertisement, and notes only] 324 mm x 200 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 118, 90
      Autograph of the motto, advertisement, and notes to the poem, untitled but numbered 5. and identified on f. 3r as "5. The progress of Poesy, a Pindaric Ode", in MS instructions to Dodsley for the 1768 London edition, sent in a letter, [1?] February 1768.
    - [untitled], 1 February 1768; mss.0143; poems.pppo; [3?] autograph, partial [motto, advertisement, and notes only] 324 mm x 200 mm; PRIN
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 119, 91
      Autograph of the motto, advertisement, and notes to the poem, in MS instructions to Beattie for the 1768 Glasgow edition, originally sent in a letter, 1 February 1768.
    - [untitled], [1757]; mss.0137; poems.pppo; [?] transcript
      Toynbee, "Alleged Holograph of Gray" (1928), 834
      An unlocated transcript in a copy of Designs ( 1753 ) was sold as autograph, Sotheby's ( 10 December 1913 ), lot 67 (with a facsimile).
    - The Progress of Poesy. A Pindaric Ode, 1780[?]; mss.0220; poems.pppo; 13 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/02/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled The Progress of Poesy. A Pindaric Ode (p. 33) (Ode. V. [p. 35]). The poem, which has numbered stanzas and includes the motto in Greek and attribution on the title page as well as Gray's notes to ll. 3, 13, 25, 42, 54, 66, 84, 95, 111, and 115, is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
    - [untitled], July/August 1827; mss.0262; poems.pppo; 1 transcript, partial, in the hand of William Pitter Woodhouse 191 mm x 125 mm (volume); HARV
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 9 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=36732>
      Transcript of the poem, partial, beginning "Thoughts that breathe and words that burn", in the hand of William Pitter Woodhouse, in his Commonplace book of verse and prose by various authors, July-August 1827, vol. i (82 leaves), f. 80v.
    - Ode, [after 1773]; mss.0267; poems.pppo; [?] transcript in the hand of John Freeman Milward Dovaston 190mm x 120mm (volume); YALE
      Parks, Stephen et al. (ed.), Osborn Collection First-Line Index. New Haven: Beinecke Library, Yale University, 2005, 101, item A1906
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 16 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10642>
      Transcript in the hand of John Freeman Milward Dovaston, entitled Ode, in his autograph Select, and Miscellaneous Poems, Scraps, Mottos &c, 1773 and later, a Commonplace book of verse by Dovaston and others.
    - Progress of poesy, 3rd August 1824; mss.0290; poems.pppo; 1 transcript (ll. 83-94) in the hand of R. Barneby; FOLG
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Dec. 2012. Folger Shakespeare Library. 15 February 2013. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=295129>
      Transcript of 12 lines (ll. 83-94) in the hand of R. Barneby, beginning "Far from the sun and summer gale" (III.1) and signed "R. Barneby Aug.t 3rd. 1824."
  - Satire on the Heads of Houses; or, Never a Barrel the Better Herring, O Cambridge, attend; 1884; poems.sahh
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 76-77
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 280-282
    According to
    Starr/Hendrickson
    , possibly written in the late 1740s or early 1750s when Gray's criticism of the University authorities was particularly severe. First published in
    Gosse (ed.), Works (1884), vol. I, 134-135
    , where the poem is dated "about 1765".
    - Satire on the Heads of Houses; or, Never a Barrel the Better Herring, [between 1747 and 1765]; mss.0145; poems.sahh; [?] autograph; [privately owned]
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 120, 91
      Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues (1971), Evans sale (27-29 November 1845), lot 615(?), 10, Sotheby's sale (28 August 1851), lot 53(?), 42, Sotheby's sale (4 August 1854), lot 229(?), 70
      W[right]., Catalogue (1851), [lot 53?,] 10
      Autograph, owned (1884) by Lord Houghton.
    - Lines on the Heads of Houses. Never a barrell better Herring, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0146; poems.sahh; 2 transcript in the hand of John Mitford 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 121, 91
      Transcript in the hand of John Mitford, here entitled Lines on the Heads of Houses. Never a barrell better Herring and beginning "Oh! Cambridge attend", in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", ff. 186-187.
    - Lines on the Heads of Houses. Never barrell a better Herring, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0144; poems.sahh; 2 transcript in the hand of John Mitford 180 mm x 110 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), 91
      Transcript, entitled Lines on the Heads of Houses. Never barrell a better Herring, in the hand of John Mitford, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, ff. 30r, 31r.
  - [Sketch of his Own Character], Too poor for a bribe and too proud to importune; 1775; poems.skoc
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 77
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 236-238
    Written in 1761, not earlier than April. First published, untitled, in a note in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), 264.
    - [untitled], [after 1771]; mss.0147; poems.skoc; 1 transcript in the hand of William Mason; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 122, 91
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 31
      Transcript in the hand of William Mason, here untitled, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1111.
  - Song I, 'Midst beauty and pleasure's gay triumphs, to languish; 1797; poems.sng1
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 99
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 240-241
    Written before October 1761 at the request of Gray's friend Henrietta Speed. Walpole transcribed and sent it in a letter to Caroline Campbell, Countess of Ailesbury, 28 November 1761. First published, beginning "With beauty, with pleasure surrounded, to languish", in Pope's Works (1797), ed. Joseph Warton, vol. II, 285n. Entitled Amatory Lines by Mitford and
    Northup, Bibliography (1917), 61
    - Song, [after 1771]; mss.0148; poems.sng1; 1 transcript in the hand of William Mason; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 123, 91
      Transcript in the hand of William Mason, here entitled Song and annotated "From an interlind & corrected Copy", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1105.
    - [untitled], July 1790; mss.0149; poems.sng1; [1?] transcript in the hand of Hester Lynch Thrale; HULI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 124, 91
      Balderston, K. C. (ed.), Thraliana (Oxford, 1942)
      Transcript in the hand of Hester Lynch Thrale, untitled and beginning "With Beauty, with Pleasure surrounded--to languish", in her MS Thraliana, vol. V, 153.
    - [untitled], mss.0150; poems.sng1; 2 transcript in an unidentified hand; MOLI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 125, 91
      Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues (1971), Sotheby's sale (28 August 1851), lot 53(?), 41, Sotheby's sale (4 August 1854), lot 228(?), 69
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, apparently copied from an autograph MS, bound with Gray's copy of Odes ( 1757 ).
    - [untitled], [after 1761]; mss.0151; poems.sng1; 1 transcript in an unidentified hand 230 mm x 190 mm; HULI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 126, 91
      Richardson, Gayle M., "HM 12550". E-mail to the editor, 15 November 2006
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, untitled and beginning "With beauty with pleasure surrounded to languish", together with MS 0159, annotated in the hand of Horace Walpole "The following two poems were given to Mr. Jacob by (Miss Speed) Countess of Vim, who told him they (were) written by Mr. Gray".
    - [?], [17??]; mss.0214; poems.sng1; [1?] transcript in the hand of James Beattie 250 mm x 200 mm; UABD
      Transcript in the hand of James Beattie, prefaced in his hand "The following Songs being found amongst the Author's papers, with marginal corrections by his own hand which serve to authenticate them, are here inserted chiefly of that account. The former, if not the latter, has undoubtedly a degree of Lyrical merit appropriated to that species of composition."
    - [untitled], [late 18th century]; mss.0286; poems.sng1; 1 transcript in an unidentified hand 220mm x 130mm (volume); YALE
      Parks, Stephen et al. (ed.), Osborn Collection First-Line Index. New Haven: Beinecke Library, Yale University, 2005, 1058, item W2376
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 23 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10628>
      Transcript, beginning "With beauty, with pleasure surrounded, to languish---", in a late 18th century, anonymous Commonplace Book (4 vols.), which contains more than 1100 numbered extracts from works by various authors; a number of the poems are signed or initialed by William Warren Porter (1776-1804) or his sister, so possibly the books were compiled by a member of the Porter family.
  - Song II, Thyrsis, when we parted, swore; 1791; poems.sng2
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 99-100
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 242-243
    Written in October 1761 at the request of Gray's friend Henrietta Speed. First published in The European Magazine 19 (February 1791), 152.
    - [untitled], [before the end of October 1761]; mss.0154; poems.sng2; 1 autograph, revised; MOLI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 127, 91, with GrT 216, 101, on the verso
      Jones, Thomas Gray, Scholar (1937), "Register of Gray Autograph Manuscripts", VI. 20(a) Verses on Miss Speed, 181
      Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues (1971), Evans sale (27-29 November 1845), lot 624(?), 11, Sotheby's sale (12 August 1847), lot 90, 27, Sotheby's sale (28 August 1851), lot 53(?), 41, Sotheby's sale (4 August 1854), lot 228, 69
      Autograph, revised, here untitled, bound into Gray's copy of Odes ( 1757 ).
    - Song, [after 1771]; mss.0155; poems.sng2; 1 transcript in the hand of William Mason; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 128, 91
      Transcript in the hand of William Mason, here entitled Song, together with a list of variants entitled First Expressions, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1106.
    - [untitled], 28 November 1761; mss.0156; poems.sng2; [1?] transcript in the hand of Horace Walpole; YALE
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 129, 91
      Catalogue of a Sotheby's sale (5 December 1921), lot 6
      Lewis, W. S. et al. (eds.), Horace Walpole's Correspondence (New Haven, 1974), vol. 38, 144-145
      Transcript, here untitled, in the hand of Horace Walpole, in a letter to Caroline Campbell, Countess of Ailesbury, 28 November 1761.
    - [untitled], [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0157; poems.sng2; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 130, 92
      Transcript of MS 0154, untitled, in the hand of John Mitford, including variant readings, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", f. 73.
    - Thyrsis, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0152; poems.sng2; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 10, 12] 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Transcript, here entitled Thyrsis, of variants of ll. 10 and 12 in the hand of John Mitford, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", f. 181r.
    - Thyrsis, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0208; poems.sng2; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 10, 12] and crossed out 180 mm x 110 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Transcript, here entitled Thyrsis, of variants of ll. 10 and 12 in the hand of John Mitford (crossed out), in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, f. 29r.
    - [untitled], July 1790; mss.0158; poems.sng2; [1?] transcript in the hand of Hester Lynch Thrale; HULI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 131, 92
      Transcript in the hand of Hester Lynch Thrale, untitled and beginning "Thyrsis when he left me swore", in her MS Thraliana, vol. V, 153.
    - [untitled], [after 1761]; mss.0159; poems.sng2; 1 transcript in an unidentified hand 230 mm x 190 mm; HULI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 132, 92
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, here untitled and beginning "Thyrsis when he left me swore", together with MS 0151, annotated in the hand of Horace Walpole "The following two poems were given to Mr. Jacob by (Miss Speed) Countess of Vim, who told him they (were) written by Mr. Gray".
    - [untitled], [between 1776 and 1804]; mss.0153; poems.sng2; 1 transcript in the hand of John Phillipps 193 mm x 160 mm; BDLN; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Duke Humfrey's, Bodleian Library, on 02/10/2006.
      Crum (ed.), First-Line Index (1969), vol. II, 953, item T2676
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=83634>
      Transcript in the hand of John Phillipps, endorsed beneath the poem "Mr. Gray", in a volume of collected verse, copied from manuscripts, printed editions and newspapers, by John Phillipps of the Middle Temple and Exeter College, Oxford, 1776-1804 (Summary Catalogue, 45759).
    - [?], [17??]; mss.0215; poems.sng2; [1?] transcript in the hand of James Beattie 250 mm x 200 mm; UABD
    - Song By Mr Gray, mss.0254; poems.sng2; 1 transcript c. 230 mm x 185 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/07/2010.
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 9 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=140012>
      Transcript of the poem, in a volume entitled Manuscript Poems (ff. vii+94), in the Holland House Papers, the papers of the Fox and Fox-Strangways families, Barons Holland and Earls of Ilchester, of Holland House, Kensington.
    - Lines by..., [between 1793 and 1800]; mss.0285; poems.sng2; 1 transcript in the hand of Anne Jane (Gore) Hamilton 250mm x 200mm (volume); YALE
      Parks, Stephen et al. (ed.), Osborn Collection First-Line Index. New Haven: Beinecke Library, Yale University, 2005, 873, item T2582
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 23 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10650>
      Transcript in the hand of Anne Jane (Gore) Hamilton, entitled Lines by..., in her autograph Commonplace book of original verse and verses contributed by her friends (1 v.; 135 p.).
  - Sonnet [on the Death of Mr Richard West], In vain to me the smiling mornings shine; 1775; poems.sorw
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 92
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 64-68
    Composed at Stoke Poges shortly after the death of Richard West, Gray's closest friend, on 1 June 1742. First published, entitled Sonnet On the Death of Mr. Richard West, in Mason's Poems ( 1775 ), 60.
    - Sonnet, August 1742; mss.0160; poems.sorw; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      , facsimile in
      Gosse (ed.), Works (1884), vol. iv, frontispiece
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 133, 92
      Autograph fair copy, here entitled Sonnet and annotated "at Stoke, Aug: 1742", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol I, 284. It is listed as "West (Richard) Sonnet, on him" in Gray's index to vol II.
    - Sonnet, On the Death of Richard West Esq., [between 1771 and 1820]; mss.0202; poems.sorw; 1 transcript in an unidentified hand; UMAN
      Young, Anne, "Re: English MS 656/74". Two e-mails to the editor, 16 and 18 August 2006
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, probably addressed to Hester Lynch Thrale, in a section of the Thrale Piozzi Collection described as "Poems in various hands, some initialled or signed, other copied... there are 135 items, dated between c. 1735 and 1820." Beneath the sonnet is written "This is the Sonnet I was mentioning to you of Grays which you did not recollect...".
    - Sonnet on the Death of Mr. Richard West, 1780[?]; mss.0227; poems.sorw; 4 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/03/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled Sonnet on the Death of Mr. Richard West (p. 105) (Sonnet. [p. 107]). The poem is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
  - [Sophonisba Masinissae. Epistola], Egregium accipio promissi Munus amoris; 1775; poems.lt23
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 153-156 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 318-321 (with English prose translation)
    Written before mid-May 1742. First published in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), section III, letter X. Mason is the only source for this (probably conflated) letter, dated [27 May 1742], in which Gray originally sent the poem to Richard West.
    - Sophonisba Massinissae. Epistola, 1780[?]; mss.0236; poems.lt23; 6 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/03/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled Sophonisba Massinissae. Epistola (p. 17) (Epistola. [p. 19]). The poem, which contains three variant readings ("fata" for "fama" [l. 15], "Consideramque" for "Credideramque" [l. 44] and "resurgat" for "recursat" [l. 51]), is part of a section called Latin Pieces, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 24), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
  - Stanzas to Mr Bentley, In silent gaze the tuneful choir among; 1775; poems.stbe
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 98
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 152-155
    Written probably in 1752 in recognition of Richard Bentley's drawings for the 1753 edition, the publication of which Horace Walpole was overseeing. First published in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), 227-228.
    - [?], [after 1771]; mss.0162; poems.stbe; 1 transcript, in the hand of William Mason; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 134, 92
      Transcript in the hand of William Mason, wanting the ends of ll. 26-28, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1107.
    - [?], [17??]; mss.0161; poems.stbe; [?] transcript in the hand of James Beattie 250 mm x 200 mm; UABD
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), 92
      Transcript in the hand of James Beattie, annotated in his hand "These verses were written in compliment to Mr Bentley for the designs which he drew to several of Mr Gray's poems, and which were engraved by Grignion, and published by Dodsley. Those persons who have only seen the graved prints will be inclined to think the panegyrick outreé. The Drawings themselves in the possession of Mr Walpole have undoubtedly much more merit. The original M.S. is unfortunately torn at the bottom which occasions a chasm in the last stanzas."
    - [untitled], July/August 1827; mss.0257; poems.stbe; 1 transcript, partial, in the hand of William Pitter Woodhouse 191 mm x 125 mm (volume); HARV
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 9 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=36731>
      Transcript of the poem, partial, beginning "Enough for me, if to some feeling breast", in the hand of William Pitter Woodhouse, in his Commonplace book of verse and prose by various authors, July-August 1827, vol. i (82 leaves), f. 67.
  - [Tophet], Such Tophet was; so looked the grinning fiend; 1769 (pr. 1783); poems.tapr
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 75
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 100-103
    Written c. 1749 under a sketch of the Rev. Henry Etough drawn by William Mason. First published, ll. 1-2, 5-8, as On Mr. E---'s being ordained and beginning "Such Tophet was--so grum'd the bawling Fiend", in The London Magazine 52 (June 1783), 296. The text, ll. 1-2, 5-8, was also issued on an etching by Michael Tyson of the drawing of Tophet by Mason, 1769.
    - Inscription on a portrait, [after 1771]; mss.0163; poems.tapr; 1 transcript in the hand of William Mason; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 136, 92
      Transcript of ll. 1-2, 5-8, 3-4 in the hand of William Mason, here entitled Inscription on a portrait, with ll. 3-4 annotated "addition in the first Copy", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1106.
    - [?], 26 November 1769; mss.0164; poems.tapr; 1 transcript in the hand of William Cole; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 137, 92
      Transcript in the hand of William Cole, ll. 1-2, 5-8 beginning "Such Tophet was--so grinn'd the bawling Fiend", on an early state of Tyson's etching (before the text had been added), annotated by Cole on the recto "Mr. Etough, Rector of Therfeild in Hartfordshire, who had been a dissenting Teacher in a Barn at Debden at Essex, died in August 1757" and on the verso "Donum Mich Tyson Arm: & Collegii Corporis Chri Cantabr Socij Nov: 26.1769, Gulielmo Cole A: Mro".
    - [untitled], 1769; mss.0165; poems.tapr; 1 transcript in the hand of Michael Tyson c. 245 mm x 180 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.